This is
the afternoon program.
All right, good morning everybody.
We're live. All right, today's דף Daf is ל"ג. Lamed Gimmel. And
I'll just remind us what we were talking about yesterday. The issue
was:
are we talking about when you need to repay the value of
תרומה Terumah that you ate mistakenly, because במזיד B'Meizid you don't repay,
you're not considered, you know, if you will, worthy of this atonement
of paying the principal and a fifth.
So you eat it בשוגג. B'Shogeg. Is it based on a size?
I ate a volume, I repay a volume? Or is it based
on a value? It needs to be at least a פרוטה's Pruta
worth, even if it is what normally would be the requisite size.
And then רב פפא Rav Pappa introduced the view that perhaps according
to אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, who said it's a matter of value,
that it's also a matter of size. That it's actually both according
to אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, that
you need both the requisite size and a minimum value. And
that's the topic we were talking about yesterday.
And then we said that רב פפא, Rav Pappa, we cited basically
a פסוק Pasuk that refuted רב פפא. Rav Pappa. And
then we said: actually, you know, רב פפא Rav Pappa retracted his
opinion anyway. And that's exactly where we left off. The
גמרא Gemara
knows that he retracted?
How does he renounce his opinion?
Oh no, we're going to see, we're going to see, we're going
to see that you'll see. We'll see. We'll see. That's exactly what
we'll talk about. That's a perfect segue. Okay, one second.
Okay, we're picking up from ואף רב פפא הדר ביה V'Af Rav
Pappa Hadar Bei דתניא D'Tanya and then there's like this little circle,
it's like about, I don't know, call it six-seven lines from
right
above from wherever the גמרא Gemara gets wide. See that? ואף רב
פפא הדר ביה V'Af Rav Pappa Hadar Bei on ל"ב Lamed Bet
עמוד ב. Amud Bet. Got it? You got it? ל"ב Lamed Bet
עמוד ב? Amud Bet?
Yeah, ל"ב Lamed Bet עמוד ב Amud Bet ואף רב פפא הדר
ביה. V'Af Rav Pappa Hadar Bei. ב's Bet the first word on
the line, it's basically just a little bit above where the רבנו
חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel begins. I'm trying to just orient you.
Okay, I'm going to go on. ואף רב פפא הדר ביה דתניא
וחטא את בשגגה. V'Af Rav Pappa Hadar Bei D'Tanya VeCheit At Bishgaga.
This is a פסוק Pasuk about eating תרומה Terumah as a matter
of fact, and מעילה, Me'ilah, I should say. And when you do
that, if that you bring this אשם מעילות, Asham Me'ilot, you bring
an אשם Asham קרבן. Korban.
So you only do that if you commit this מעילה Me'ilah בשגגה,
Bishgaga, פרט למזיד. Prat L'Meizid. If you...
however, if you do it במזיד, B'Meizid, you do not bring this
אשם. Asham. Then the גמרא Gemara questions and it's really not going
to hold up this logic, so the גמרא's Gemara going to reverse
itself right away. ולא דינו? V'Lo Dino? But what do you mean?
Why do you need a פסוק Pasuk to tell me this? Could
I not have figured this out? משאר מצוות שחייב בהן כרת פוטר
בהן את המזיד.
MiSha'ar Mitzvot SheHayav Bahen Karet
Poter Bahen Et HaMeizid. So other מצוות Mitzvot where you're חייב Hayav
כרת, Karet, you're פטור Patur במזיד B'Meizid
from
let's say קרבנות. Korbanot. I'm not talking about like you're פטור Patur
if you commit, you know, מחלל שבת Mechallel Shabbat במזיד, B'Meizid, but
let's say חלב Chelev or דם Dam or something like that. That
there's an עונש Onesh of כרת. Karet. If I eat it בשוגג,
B'Shogeg, but if I do it במזיד, B'Meizid, then I don't bring
this קרבן. Korban.
מעילה שאין בה כרת, Me'ilah SheEin Ba Karet, מעילה Me'ilah does not
have כרת, Karet, rather it's מיתה בידי שמים, Mita B'Yedei Shamayim, אינו
דין שפטר את המזיד? Eino Din ShePatar Et HaMeizid? Should it not
be that you're פטור Patur במזיד B'Meizid now? Why
why what's the reasoning for that?
Presumably because מיתה בידי שמים, Mita B'Yedei Shamayim,
according
to this first way of understanding, maybe worse. Right? So מיתה בידי
שמים's Mita B'Yedei Shamayim worse than כרת, Karet, so כרת Karet that's
easier, you get off, certainly מיתה בידי שמים, Mita B'Yedei Shamayim, you
know, you
I thought it was...
Yeah, no, no, I'm telling you it's not going to hold up.
So... okay. לא אם אמרת בשאר מצוות שכן לא חייב בהן מיתה
תאמר במעילה שחייב בהן מיתה?
Lo Im Amarta BeSha'ar
Mitzvot SheKen Lo Hayav Bahen Mita Tomar BeMe'ilah SheHayav Bahen Mita? So
no, the other ones, that's not really true, because בשאר מצוות BeSha'ar
Mitzvot you're not חייב Hayav מיתה
בידי שמים, Mita B'Yedei Shamayim, rather you know you wouldn't say that...
מעילה Me'ilah you are חייב Hayav מיתה בידי שמים, Mita B'Yedei Shamayim,
which is now viewed you know so... what's going on here? תלמוד
לומר בשגגה פרט למזיד. Talmud Lomar Bishgaga Prat LeMeizid. So no, therefore
anyway the point they're saying is we'll see, I'm not going to...
that's... I'm just getting to the end. So therefore you need a
פסוק, Pasuk, because you wouldn't have figured it out. ואמר ליה רב
נחמן בר יצחק לרב חייא בר אבין האי תנא מעיקרא אלימי לכרת
ולבסוף
אלימי למיתה. VeAmar Lei Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak LeRav Chiya Bar Avin
Hai Tanna MeIkkara Alimei LeKaret VeSof Alimei LeMita.
So which is it? In other words, it goes back and forth.
Oh, this one is כרת Karet so it's worse. And this is,
oh no, this one is מיתה בידי שמים Mita B'Yedei Shamayim so
it's worse. But it's the same... so which is it? Which is
worse? Right? It reverses itself. No no the other ones have have
this. Oh no no this one had you know this one had
that. So at the end of the day which which is the
worse one? At the beginning it sounds like that כרת kareit is
worse.
Therefore you can't say it because because the other ones have you
know the other ones have כרת. kareit. Then it says then they're
saying no no this one is worse because מיתה בידי שמים. mita
bidei shamayim. Okay, so which which is worse? Is כרת kareit worse
or is מיתה בידי שמים mita bidei shamayim worse? And we're going
to explain, the גמרא's Gemara going to give other explanations as to
what this whole thing was. So I'm being a little bit vague
because the explanation's going to hold up. But anyway the point being
though it seems it seems to highlight you know one versus the
other. מיתה... mita... You see that? The מיתה בידי שמים mita bidei
shamayim versus כרת. kareit. That that's what's being highlighted and it transitions
to which is being worse.
Okay, then he says ואמר ליה הכי קאמר. va-amar lei hachi ka-amar.
So this this is what I this is what I mean to
say.
לא, Lo, you know you can't compare one to the other. אי
אמרת בשאר מצוות, I amarta be-she'ar mitzvot, that's what we started out
by saying, בשאר מצוות שכן לא חייב בהם מיתה פחות מכזית. be-she'ar
mitzvot she-kein lo chayav ba-hem mita pachot mi-kezayit. So we're saying no
no we don't mean we don't mean what the first way of
looking at it was focusing on the magnitude of the punishment. כרת
Kareit
worse, מיתה בידי שמים mita bidei shamayim is worse and it kind
of flip-flops back and forth for that. So what it means to
say by it is this:
don't focus on the actual punishment but focus on like the process,
in other words the crime. Focus on the crime. So שאר מצוות
she'ar mitzvot
you won't be
חייב מיתה בפחות מכזית. chayav mita be-pachot mi-kezayit. תאמר במעילה שחייב בה
מיתה בפחות מכזית. Tomar be-me'ilah she-chayav bah mita be-pachot mi-kezayit.
However מעילה me'ilah you're liable even if you take, if you מעל
mo'eil on something that's פחות מכזית, pachot mi-kezayit, less than a כזית.
kezayit. So therefore you can't make a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. That's
what the גמרא Gemara tried to do, right? He says oh you
brought the פסוק, pasuk, what do you mean isn't it a קל
וחומר? kal va-chomer? So the answer is no, it's not a קל
וחומר kal va-chomer because because at the end of the day the
other sins, forget forget the punishment for a moment,
you're חייב chayav only on a כזית, kezayit, whereas מעילה me'ilah
it's even less than a כזית. kezayit. So therefore I wouldn't have
necessarily known you know about קרבנות. korbanot. So therefore I needed a
פסוק pasuk to tell you that you don't you don't bring it.
ואמר ליה אח תנוח דעתך שהנחת את דעתי. Va-amar lei ach tanu'ach
da'at’cha she-hinachta et da’ati. This was a conversation between, actually it doesn't
actually say... it says רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
to רב חייא בר אבא, Rav Chiyya bar Abba, right? So so
he says ah you know thank you, you you know basically תנוח
דעתך, tanu'ach da'at’cha, you know you should get reward because your mind
be at ease basically because you eased my mind because it was
something that was really bothering me. ואמר ליה, Va-amar lei, so then
so then we said wait a minute, מאי ניחותא? mai nichuta?
How does this hold up? דרבה ורב ששת שדו בה נרגא. de-Rabba
ve-Rav Sheshet shadu bah narga. Like you know they like kind of
like you know they made an opening the size of whatever, they
threw an axe into this. Basically they you know they
they destroyed this whole thing, they this doesn't this doesn't hold up.
מאן שמעת ליה דאמר מזיד במעילה במיתה? Man shamat lei de-amar meizid
be-me'ilah be-mita?
So the question is list is this: we know that in the
תורה Torah it says that if
you do this מעילה וחטאה בשגגה, me'ilah ve-chat’ah bi-shgagah, then you bring
this אשם. asham. So what happens if you if you do it
במזיד? be-meizid? It doesn't actually say what happens if you do it
במזיד. be-meizid.
So this is the question. So מזיד במעילה במיתה, meizid be-me'ilah be-mita,
this is assuming that you know it's מיתה, mita, that's what we
just said a second ago, right? Because others you get the punishment
if you do it only בכזית, be-kezayit, but מעילה me'ilah you get
this מיתה mita even if you do it less than a כזית.
kezayit. Like who's the one that says you are held liable?
That's רבי. Rebbi. דתניא מזיד במעילה רבי אומר במיתה וחכמים אומרים באזהרה.
De-tanya meizid be-me'ilah Rebbi omer
be-mita va-chachamim omrim be-azharah. No just an אזהרה, azharah, you're over on
a on a לאו, lav, but not מיתה. mita. So obviously it
has to be רבי Rebbi because the חכמים chachamim say you're not
חייב מיתה במעילה במזיד. chayav mita be-me'ilah be-meizid.
Okay, so it's רבי. Rebbi. ומאי טעמא דרבי? Ve-mai ta’ama de-Rebbi? אמר
רבי ואמרי לה רבי אבהו Amar Rebbi ve-amri lah Rabbi Abbahu גמר
חטא חטא מתרומה. gamar cheit cheit mi-trumah. So
since again the תורה Torah by מעילה במזיד me'ilah be-meizid does not
say what your punishment is and רבי Rebbi
has
to infer it. Since he says it's במזיד, be-meizid, he has to
infer it from elsewhere. And where do you from where do you
infer that? מתרומה. Mi-trumah. מה תרומה במיתה, Ma trumah be-mita, that we
know because that's a specific פסוק. pasuk. מתו בו כי יחללוהו Metu
vo ki yechalelu’hu I think is the פסוק, pasuk, but at any
rate there's פסוקים psukim about that. מה תרומה במיתה אף מעילה במיתה
Ma trumah be-mita af me'ilah be-mita because it talks about חטא חטא.
cheit cheit.
So okay, so then so he learns it from
from
תרומה. trumah. ומינה, U-minah, מה תרומה בכזית אף מעילה
בכזית.
ma trumah be-kezayit af
me'ilah be-kezayit. If we're already going to learn that, we know that
תרומה trumah the minimum amount to be liable for is a כזית.
kezayit. So too with מעילה me'ilah the minimum amount to be liable
for is a כזית. kezayit. But wait didn't we just say a
second ago that you know מעילה me'ilah should be more חמור? chamur?
More because you're even חייב chayav on a פחות מכזית, pachot mikezayit,
right? That was how he answered it. In other words, you couldn't
have drawn a קל וחומר kal vachomer to other מצוות, mitzvot, right?
Saying that was our whole point. First you start out by saying
what do you need a פסוק pasuk for, couldn't you figure it
out another, couldn't you have figured out a קל וחומר kal vachomer
by relating it to other מצוות, mitzvot, right? And we said no
you can't figure out the קל וחומר kal vachomer from other מצוות,
mitzvot, if again if there's a קל kal and a חומר, chomer,
right? So which is the קל kal and which is the חומר?
chomer? So we would have thought other מצוות mitzvot were the חומר
chomer to the so because and therefore מעילה me'ila would be more
קל kal and therefore don't need the פסוק. pasuk. And he says
no the other מצוות mitzvot are the קל kal because you're חייב
chayav only in a כזית kezayit and מעילה me'ila is the חומר
chomer because you're חייב chayav less than a כזית. kezayit. That's what
he said, right? But now he's saying if you're learning it from
תרומה, truma, you need a כזית. kezayit. So it's the same.
So that destroys the whole that whole reason for the פסוק, pasuk,
right? It's been axed. It's been axed.
Okay so anyway so again that our step was we had a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, does it hold, does it not hold up?
So what then the conversation between those two rabbis, someone said someone
explained why why you need it, you wouldn't have been able to
figure it out, therefore you have a פסוק. pasuk. So then and
that only works according to רבי Rebbi that says מעילה me'ila במזיד
bemazid you get מיתה. mita. But the problem is the same רבי
Rebbi who would hold מעילה me'ila במזיד bemazid you get מיתה mita
would also hold that it's with a כזית. kezayit. And the whole
point of the קל וחומר kal vachomer was even מעילה me'ila was
less than a כזית. kezayit. So now what so what do you
do, right? Okay now on this because take a step even further
back, a whole reason why we brought all this was to show
you how רב פפא Rav Pappa changes his mind, right? So now
that's what we're going to get to. ומתקיף לה רב פפא Umaskif
lah Rav Pappa so on all this that we just said ממאי
דרבי כרבנן סבירא ליה mimay d'Rebbi k'rabanan svira leh
how do we know that רבי Rebbi holds like the רבנן? rabanan?
We don't mean the רבנן rabanan who he's disagreeing with about the
punishment for מעילה me'ila because obviously he doesn't hold like them but
what we mean by that is
that he holds like the רבנן rabanan because
the מחלוקת machloket רבנן rabanan and אבא שאול Abba Shaul because remember
the question was is it a size or is it a value?
So רבי Rebbi saying it's a כזית kezayit is talking about a
size, right?
So that's רבנן. rabanan. רבנן rabanan are focused on size. Because if
it would have been like אבא שאול Abba Shaul he would have
said like a פרוטה pruta is worth, right?
Anyway so he says ומתקיף לה רב פפא umaskif lah Rav Pappa
ממאי דרבי כרבנן סבירא ליה mimay d'Rebbi k'rabanan svira leh דילמא כאבא
שאול סבירא ליה dilma k'Abba Shaul svira leh דאמר יש בה שוה
פרוטה אף על גב דלית בה כזית.
d'amar yesh bah shaveh pruta af al
gav d'leit bah kezayit.
So he says no maybe how do you know maybe he holds
like אבא שאול Abba Shaul that requires a שוה פרוטה shaveh pruta
even if it doesn't have a כזית. kezayit. Oh wait a minute,
רב פפא Rav Pappa is the one that says you need both,
right? Isn't that what isn't that what we started out by saying?
והא רב פפא הוא דאמר דאבא שאול תרתי בעי. V'ha Rav Pappa
hu d'amar d'Abba Shaul tartei ba'i.
What do you mean אבא שאול Abba Shaul says how do you
know that he holds like רבי maybe he holds like אבא שאול
Abba Shaul that focuses on value? But according to רב פפא Rav
Pappa what we originally said is אבא שאול Abba Shaul yes he
has a value criteria but he also had a size criteria so
he'd still say a כזית. kezayit. So what are you saying maybe
he doesn't hold a כזית? kezayit? According to the way you tried
to explain it אבא שאול Abba Shaul holds both the כזית kezayit
and a פרוטה's pruta worth. אלא שמע מינה הדר ביה. Ela shema
mina hadar beh. So he must have reversed his opinion. In order
to pose this question on what we were just saying he must
have said okay אבא שאול Abba Shaul only holds a פרוטה pruta
and not a כזית kezayit because that's how we said. Otherwise it
still would have been like both.
Get that?
We all good?
Sort of? Yeah? Okay.
All right so anyway so again that was a little complicated but
it'll get a little bit better from here.
Okay now remember
we were trying to figure out what that so so we were
done with the רב פפא Rav Pappa part but now that we
quoted this whole ברייתא, baraita, and again the reason we quoted the
ברייתא baraita was to prove that רב פפא Rav Pappa reverses opinion
as to what אבא שאול held. We're going to talk a little
bit more about this ברייתא. baraita. So again the we were trying
to explain how it seemed like we reversed ourselves between מיתה mita
versus כרת karet which is more חמור. chamur. So now how do
you explain it? And we ended up adding in a few words,
right? So the first the first way we ended up explaining it
was no other מצוות mitzvot
you are liable only in a כזית's kezayit worth whereas מעילה me'ila
you're liable even less than
a even less than a כזית's kezayit size. Okay so the
other way the other way of saying it is הכי גמר לא.
hachi gamar lo. In other words you were trying to say that
other מצוות mitzvot were more חמור? chamur? No maybe other מצוות mitzvot
and מעילה me'ila was more קל kal so and what would apply
to one would certainly apply to the other. No maybe the other
way around מעילה me'ila is more חמור chamur why? לא אמרת בשאר
מצוות Lo amart b'sha'ar mitzvot so other מצוות mitzvot would be different
than מעילה me'ila because שלא עשה בהן שאינו מתכוין כמתכוין. shelo asa
bahen she'eino mitkaven k'mitkaven. Other מצוות mitzvot you have to
actually be במזיד bemazid
or even in general is מתכוין mitkaven basically you have to have
כוונה kavana for it. versus אינו מתכוון eino miskaven where where you're
not trying to do it. So in other מצוות mitzvos there's a
difference, right? So שאינו מתכוון, she'eino miskaven, let's say talk about שבת
Shabbos for a second. שאינו מתכוון לחתוך את התלוש וחתך את המחובר
שפטור. she'eino miskaven lachtoch es hatallush vechasach es hamichubar shepattur.
So one of the מלאכות melachos or or is harvesting, right? Like
a קוצר. kotzer. And you only harvest if you're actually let's say
plucking a fruit, right? You know, it's attached to the tree and
now we remove it from the tree. So... Oh wait, I'm getting
a call from my family. Everyone hold on a second. Hello?
Okay, yes, I will. Thanks.
Last night was worse than the night before. Now it's the rest
of the family.
Anyway, so in other מצוות mitzvos there's a difference. So as I
was mentioning, שבת, Shabbos, harvesting. Harvesting is, you know, you're plucking it,
right? You're plucking, let's say you're cutting wheat from the ground that's
attached or picking a fruit that has to be attached to the
tree. So let's say there, you know, I have two, I have
a pile... I have two fruits, one is attached and the other
isn't, and I want to like, you know, pluck, I want to
take, not pluck, I want to take the one
that's
already been that's detached. And by mistake I take the one that's
attached, right? שאינו מתכוון לחתוך את התלוש. she'eino miskaven lachtoch es hatallush.
You're not really חותך chotech if it's already תלוש. tallush. But you
know, I want to take it, right? The one that's already harvested
so to speak, the one that's already plucked, that's fine, right? You
know, I could take my banana and eat it on שבת Shabbos
from my fruit bowl essentially, right? So if I wanted to do
that, but oh by mistake I ended up chopping off the one
that's attached. פטור, Pattur, פטור pattur because you know, that's not what
I wanted to do. אבל תאמר במעילה שאינו מתכוון להתחמם בגיזי חולין
ונתחמם בגיזי עולה שמעל. aval tomar beme'ilah she'eino miskaven lehischamem begizei chullin
venischamem begizei olah shema'al.
But let's say I wanted to, yeah, wrap myself in a cloak
and I wanted to use the חולין chullin one and ended up
wrapping myself in the עולה olah skin. I wasn't מתכוון. miskaven. I'm
still מועל. mo'el. So מעילה me'ilah is more חמור. chamur. So that's,
you know, so that's another way of saying why מעילה me'ilah is
more חמור chamur than other מצוות. mitzvos. רב חמא בר יצחק אמר
הכי קאמר. Rav Chama bar Yitzchak amar hachi ka'amar. So this is
another way of setting up the
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. לא אם אמרת בשאר מצוות שכן לא מתחייב
בהן שאין מתעסק כמתעסק. lo im amarta bish'ar mitzvos sheken lo mis'chayev
bahen she'ein mis'asek kemis'asek.
Similar. There's מתכוון miskaven versus מתעסק, mis'asek, but it's the same idea.
מתעסק Mis'asek is like let's say the classic case of מתעסק. mis'asek.
Let's say, let's say I'm doing my juggling act, right, with knives.
And then I or you know, you know people throw knives at
people by the wall, you know, don't hit them. So I'm throwing
my knife and then and then, you know, as it as it
passes by, such a clean cut, it goes through an animal and
cuts the, you know, trachea and esophagus, right? It שחט shachat it.
So would that be good or not? That would be מתעסק. mis'asek.
I'm not trying to, you know, or מתעסק, mis'asek, I'm playing a
musical instrument and happens to be it's a שופר, shofar, happens to
be it's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, and I happen to be blowing,
you know, whatever the קולות. kolos.
That shifts to the general question of does it require כוונה kavana
for מצווה? mitzvah?
Right, that's what I'm saying. It's close to מתכוון. miskaven. But מתעסק
mis'asek is like, I you know, I'm just like, I'm not even
you know, trying to like שחט shachat this animal at all. I'm
not, didn't even know it was there, you know, but it ended
up...
Or if you're reading if you're reading through a ספר תורה
sefer Torah and it
happens to be all three parts of the שמע. Shema.
Right. So that's the same, yeah. Anyway, so in other cases it's
that's מתעסק. mis'asek. שכן לא מתחייב בהן שאין מתעסק כמתעסק. sheken lo
mis'chayev bahen she'ein mis'asek kemis'asek. For instance, שאינו מתכוון להגביה את התלוש
וחתך את המחובר שפטור. she'eino miskaven lehagbi'ah es hatallush vechatech es hamichubar
shepattur. Right? I wanted to again, raise my same idea, raise my
fruit, you know, take my banana out of the whatever, out of
the fruit bowl. But I ended up taking the banana off the
tree. וחתך את המחובר שפטור. vechatech es hamichubar shepattur. תאמר במעילה שאם
הושיט ידו לכלי ליטול חפץ וסך ידו בשמן של קודש שמעל. tomar
beme'ilah she'im hoshit yado likli litol chefetz vesach yado beshemen shel kodesh
shema'al. Right? So this is a little bit different. That's why this
is where you see the difference between מתעסק mis'asek versus a... מתעסק.
mis'asek. In the first case I actually wanted to take the עולה,
olah, right? When I wanted to use the skin, I wanted to
warm myself with the coat, I took
a coat, but I just ended up taking the wrong one. I
took the עולה olah coat, right? The, you know, versus the, you
know, versus my leather jacket. But over here, this was totally incidental.
Like let's say I wanted to, I don't know, let's say my
ball dropped in a bowl of olive oil and I wanted to
get the ball out. But my hand went through the bowl of
olive oil, right? And but this was, you know, הקדש hekdesh olive
oil, whatever, you know.
So and I needed it vis-a-vis getting the ball, my hand went
through oil and now it's סיכה. sichah. So I got הנאה hana'ah
from it because everyone was, you know, especially back then everyone was
סך. sach. So in that kind of a case, בשמן של קודש
שמעל. beshemen shel kodesh shema'al. Let's say it's like, you know, מנחה
minchah oil, you know, for מנחות. menachos. That would be קודש. kodesh.
So in that case I'm מתעסק. mis'asek. I totally didn't want to...
I didn't care about the oil. I wanted to get my ball
that fell in the, you know, the bowl of oil. Nevertheless, that's
considered מעילה. me'ilah. So that's why מעילה me'ilah would be more חמור.
chamur. That's the whole point, right? Because we started out by saying,
you know, maybe other מצוות mitzvos are more חמור. chamur. And then
no, מעילה me'ilah is more חמור. chamur. And that's why... This is
the other side as to why we couldn't tell, which is why
we needed the פסוק, pasuk, that was that whole thing. So we
gave a couple answers. The first answer was
size, an olive versus not, right? Other מצוות mitzvot you need an
olive, מעילה meilah you need less. And now these two answers are
basically intent, right? Others you're only חייב chayav with intent, מעילה meilah
you're חייבים chayavim without intent.
And מתעסק mitasek is a variation of that. Okay,
fine. All right, that's the end of that part, the end of
that ברייתא. baraita. Now we're going to go back even further. Now
remember we were talking about
giving like תרומה terumah and let's say it was חמץ, chametz, right?
If you've done anything, you gave תרומה terumah from חמץ chametz on
פסח, Pesach, right? Can you even do that? Remember all that? So
we had that ברייתא baraita before, which was just on ל"ב ע"א
lamed bet amud alef that basically said
that חמץ chametz you can't make into תרומה terumah on פסח, Pesach,
right?
אמר מר מדאמרינן, Amar mar med'amrinan, we're going to return, אמר מר
Amar mar is always a return to a statement we mentioned earlier.
אמר מר מדאמרינן Amar mar med'amrinan that this תרומה terumah won't work
on פסח Pesach with חמץ, chametz, מפריש תרומה והחמיצה. mafrish terumah vehichmitzah.
I'm sorry, קיצורו של דבר, kitsoro shel davar, in other words, how
can you even get to a point where the תרומה terumah can
be חמץ chametz and does it work or not? But
מפריש תרומה והחמיצה. mafrish terumah vehichmitzah. So it wasn't חמץ chametz at
the time, the point, it was just regular wheat or something like
that and then it became חמץ. chametz. So that's how you can,
or as we mentioned the other way of doing it is
before פסח Pesach when I'm allowed to have חמץ, chametz, I was
מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah from something, from חמץ. chametz.
This is something where we supposed to have talked about two days
ago.
Yeah, no, we're getting back to this.
Anyway, so, but אבל המפריש חמץ תרומה, aval hamafrish chametz terumah, but
it certainly will not work if I already separated it from
something on פסח Pesach that was חמץ, chametz, right? Not something that
became חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, but if I started out with
חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach and I wanted to make that into
my תרומה, terumah, אינה קדושה. einah kedoshah. So that's not even going
to become תרומה. terumah. Okay, that's what we said before. So now
we're going to say how do we know?
מנא הני מילי, mena hanei milei, how do we know? אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק אמר קרא Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar kra
תתן לו titen lo ולא לאורו. velo le'oro. So the פסוק pasuk
is ראשית דגנך תירושך ויצהרך וראשית גז צאנך תתן לו. reshit degancha
tiroshcha veyitzharecha ureshit gez tzoncha titen lo. So
this is talking about giving to the כהן kohen תרומה terumah
and basically
just stuff you need to be giving to him. So you need
to give him for instance תירושך, tiroshcha, דגן תירוש
ויצהר, dagan tirosh veyitzhar, right? You also give him the first shearings,
that's something else you give him. But תרומה terumah is from
grain, that's דגן, dagan, תירוש tirosh is wine, יצהר yitzhar is oil.
So you give and it says in the end over there in
that פסוק, pasuk, תתן לו. titen lo. So you have to be
giving, it has to be considered like a giving basically. לו, lo,
ולא לאורו. velo le'oro. You're giving it to him but not for
the fire because what can you do with stuff like that? I
mean you can't eat the חמץ, chametz, right? The most you can
do is get הנאה hana'ah from it, and that,
even if you're allowed to get
הנאה, hana'ah, that was a whole question we had anyway, but let's
say like רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili says you can get
הנאה, hana'ah, but the only הנאה hana'ah you can get is fire
because you can't eat it, right? So it has to be giving
something that he can have fully and not just
partially for fire, right? So that's how we know that if you
separated תרומה terumah from חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach it's not even
going to work. It's not considered something that he can use for
the purposes of תרומה. terumah. It's not considered a full giving to
him.
מתיבי רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע,
Matvei Rav Huna berei de Rav
Yehoshua,
okay fine now that we said that. מתיבי רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע, Matvei Rav Huna berei de Rav Yehoshua, אין
תורמין
מן הטמאה על הטהורה. ein tormin min hateme'ah al hatehorah. So forget
חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach for a moment, but let's say you
just have two piles of stuff, one stuff is טמא, tamei, one
stuff is טהור. tahor. So sometimes you do that, you can say,
oh yeah let this
תרומה terumah be what I'm taking from here but let it work
for this other pile of grain someplace else, right?
So you can't do that, you can't separate תרומה terumah from something
that's טמא tamei for something that's טהור. tahor. So it doesn't
work. אבל תרם בשוגג תרומתו תרומה. aval taram beshogeg terumato terumah. But
if you did it not במזיד, bemezid, but if you did it
בשוגג, beshogeg, you did it, you shouldn't have but you did it,
but it still works. במאי? bamai? נימא לו ולא לאורו neima lo
velo le'oro because again what can you do with תרומה טמאה? terumah
teme'ah? You can burn it, right? Let's say it was oil, you're
giving him
תרומה טמאה, terumah teme'ah, you certainly can't eat it. You can't eat
תרומה טמאה, terumah teme'ah, and the כהן kohen who's טמא tamei can't
eat תרומה terumah either,
but the כהן kohen can become טהור tahor at some point. But
the תרומה, terumah, once it's טמאה teme'ah that's it, right? You can't
like dip it in the מקוה, mikveh, it doesn't become טהור. tahor.
תרומה טמאה terumah teme'ah that's the end of it, right? remains טמאה
*Tmeiah*. But it's not, you know, completely useless. You can use it
for firewood. We've learned that a whole bunch of times, and that's
actually what you're supposed to do. You're supposed
to get rid of it that way. Okay, fine, but only thing
you can use it for is for fuel, למה לו ולא לאורה
*Lama Lo Velo Le’ora*. So if that's your פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*, right,
this same logic should apply to תרומה טמאה terumah teme'ah? *Truma Tmeiah*.
Right, we use it before for תרומה terumah, *Truma* that's חמץ chametz.
*Chametz*, right? Because oh no, the only thing you can do is
burn it. So it won't work. But wait,
if you do it בדיעבד bedi'avad *B'diavad* with תרומה terumah. טמאה *Truma
Tmeiah* and חמץ chametz *Chametz*... with תרומה terumah טמאה *Truma Tmeiah*, it
does work. But why? It's the same thing. The only thing it
could be good for is לאורה *Le'ora* and you just had a
פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* that tells you you can only give it to
him and not for the fire. So why would it work even
בדיעבד bedi'avad *B'diavad*? Get that? Okay. לא קשיא, התם היתה לו שעת
כושר, הכא לא היתה לו שעת כושר *Lo Kashya, hatam hayta lo
sha'at kosher, hacha lo hayta lo sha'at kosher*. We're going to explain
this in a second. Big difference between the two cases is, in
the case of תרומה terumah טמאה *Truma Tmeiah*, at one point it
was טהור tahor *Tahor*. So at one point it could have been
separated. So which is, you know, so therefore it works if I
separate בדיעבד bedi'avad *B'diavad* because this תרומה terumah *Truma* that is now
טמאה *Tmeiah* at one point was טהור tahor *Tahor*, had if you
will a שעת כושר *Sha'at Kosher*. So it's not out of the
פרשה *Parsha*. At some point, you know, if I would have done
it early enough and separated the תרומה terumah *Truma* from this pile,
again now טמאה *Tmeiah*, but at some point it was טהור tahor.
*Tahor*. If I would have done it when it was טהור tahor
*Tahor*, I would have been totally fine. So therefore, even now if
I do it when it's טמאה *Tmeiah*, only בדיעבד bedi'avad *B'diavad*, it
will still work. But however,
with the
חמץ chametz *Chametz*, it does not have a שעת כושר *Sha'at Kosher*.
Now how can that be? What do you mean? At some point,
you know, didn't it grow as wheat, right? Why didn't... you know,
that was okay. So, the גמרא *Gemara* explains, ולא היתה לו שעת
כושר היכי דמי *V'lo hayta lo sha'at kosher heichi dami*? How would
that work? כגון דאחמץ במחובר be-mechubar, *K'gon d'achmetz bimchubar*, right? Because again,
תרומה terumah *Truma* is only... you're only חייב *Chayiv*... it's a very
strange case, but we basically back ourselves into a corner. This is
the only answer that they can figure out right now to get
out of it. So again, תרומה terumah *Truma*... you're only... תרומה terumah
*Truma* doesn't apply to when it's מחובר *Mechubar*, right? Many other things...
you're like let's say פאה *Pe'ah*, you have לקט *Leket*, שכחה *Shich'cha*,
you know, once you start cutting it then you have לקט *Leket*...
whatever. But תרומה terumah *Truma*, it only is like once you bring
it in, like the regular way, and then you have to... you'd
have to have mounded the כרי *K'ri*, you'd have to smooth out
the כרי *K'ri*. There are a lot of whole other things. Anyway,
the point being that תרומה terumah *Truma* doesn't apply when it's still
attached to the ground. So let's say somehow you have your stalks
of wheat and then it rained, obviously, and it fermented while still
attached to the ground. I mean, whether or not that really happens
or not, I don't know. But anyway, the point is we're trying
to understand how this wheat never had a שעת כושר *Sha'at Kosher*.
So only way we can come up with that is that it
became חמץ chametz *Chametz* when it was מחובר *Mechubar*, even before it
was in the פרשה *Parsha* of תרומה teruma *Truma*. אבל אחמץ בתלוש
be-talush, *Aval achmetz b'talush*, then according to that, then even... so even
if it became חמץ chametz, *Chametz*, even if it was on פסח
Pesach. *Pesach*, but as long as it happened when it was תלוש
talush. *Talush* stuff, not stuff attached to the ground, הכא נמי דקדשה
*Hacha nami d'kadsha*? So would we say even then that would work?
אמר ליה: amar lei אין *Amar lei: In*, yeah, actually that's true.
And so if that's true, the only way to explain the ברייתא
*Baraita*... so why תרומה teruma *Truma* of חמץ chametz. *Chametz* does not
work is if it became חמץ chametz. *Chametz* while attached to the
ground and on פסח Pesach. *Pesach*.
So even בדיעבד *B'diavad* why it wouldn't work. לכתחילה l'chatchilah *Lechatchila* always
doesn't work.
Right. So, אמר amar, ליה: אין *Amar lei: In*, and then it
says from Daniel: כגזירת עירין פתגמא ומאמר קדישין שאלתא *K'gezerat irin pitgama
u-meimar kadishin she'elta*. And this גזירת עירין *Gezerat irin* as in an
עירין קדישין *Irin kaddishin*
of בני אנשא *Bnei anasha*, it's a גזירת *Gezerat* of angels and
ומאמר קדישין *U-meimar kadishin* and the מאמר *Meimar*, the utterances of those
who are holy, שאלתא *She'elta*. Yeah. And basically saying like this is
like, yes, God would agree to this. וכן מורם בי מדרשא כוותי
*V'chen morem bi-midrasha k'vati*. And this is exactly how you would explain
it,
with what I just
said. So he's very insistent on this, that this is the right
way to explain it. Okay, so כי אתא רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע *Ki ata Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua*, so now we understand
a little bit how that ברייתא *Baraita* about the תרומה *Truma* becoming
the
חמץ chametz *Chametz* on פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, and that was our case,
because it was never fit. Right. So then רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע *Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua*, so he actually disagrees because remember
because...
so he holds that...
so
anyway the point actually what we say... anyway so רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע *Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua* is commenting on this.
So, אפילו *Afilu*... so the question is, you know, let's say it
was... let's say it became חמץ chametz. *Chametz* when it was תלוש
talush, *Talush*, right? That was our
question. So we explained that if it became... the second ago, the
way we explained this was if it became חמץ chametz *Chametz* when
it was תלוש talush, *Talush*, it was... it is okay, right? Because
it has a שעת כושר *Sha'at Kosher*. Only way it's not okay
is if it became חמץ chametz. *Chametz* when it was attached, that's
what we just got through by saying. But תלוש *Talush* would be
okay. So he disagrees, he thinks it would not work even if
it became חמץ chametz when it was תלוש. So he says, אמר,
amar, now we're on the
עמוד ב. amud bet. אמר, אמר
קרא, amar kra, this is a
פסוק. pasuk ראשית, reishit, we have a פסוק pasuk
that we had before, the same פסוק pasuk that we were citing
about the תתן לו, titten lo, remember that? תתן לו, titten lo,
it's considered a הנאה, hana'ah, something you give him, but not לאור.
le-or. But again, the פסוק pasuk starts by saying ראשית. reishit. דגנך
תירושך ויצהרך ראשית
גז צאנך תתן לו.
degancha tiroshcha ve-yitzharcha reishit gez
tzonecha titten lo. So if I tell you ראשית, reishit, if I
just would have told you דגנך תירושך, degancha tiroshcha, I say ראשית.
reishit. ראשית reishit is like the beginnings of. So what if I
say a word like ראשית, reishit, what does that imply? To me
it implies, I'll ask you what it implies, what you think it
implies. If you're saying the ראשית, reishit, that means there's something after
that, right? You can't have the beginning if that's the beginning, middle,
and end. Beginning of something means that there's more coming after it,
essentially, right? It means that like this is the start of something,
there's going to be something else, right? That's essentially what we're
saying. ראשית. reishit. ששיריה ניכרין לישראל. she-shiyareiha nikkarin le-Yisrael. יצא זו שאין
שיריה ניכרין. yatza zo she-ein shiyareiha nikkarin. So I'll explain to you
what the implication is over here. Let's read the רש"י. Rashi. So
basically, when he says ששיריה ניכרין לישראל, she-shiyareiha nikkarin le-Yisrael, so again,
before I take this תרומה, everything is called טבל, tevel, right? So
if it's טבל, tevel, I can't eat it. What מתיר mattir me
to eat this stuff is taking the תרומה. So I take this
ראשית reishit and as a result, the שירי, shiyarei, what's left over,
is everything is left over,
left over can mean a lot, it doesn't necessarily mean like leftovers
from your שבת Shabbat meal where you're potentially less than you started
with. But what's left over after taking this תרומה is ששירי. she-shiyarei.
So there needs to be a distinction between what I took and
what's left over in so far as its permissibility. So that's ששיריה
ניכרין לישראל, she-shiyareiha nikkarin le-Yisrael, that I should have, by ניכרין, nikkarin,
we don't mean necessarily recognizable like I can see it, but it
means that it would have an effect. רש"י Rashi explains,
שתהא היא ראשית ואלו שיריים ניכרין שתהא היא מתירתן לישראל.
she-tehei hi reishit ve-ellu shiyaryim
nikkarin she-tehei hi mattiratan le-Yisrael. Now it's now מותר muttar because once
I take this תרומה from what was טבל, tevel, it is now
called
חולין, chullin, right? And I can eat, you know, you can eat
חולין. chullin. That's the whole point. I can
only eat חמץ. chametz Yes. Okay, fine. So that's a regular תרומה
case, but again, we're trying to figure out about תרומה of חמץ
chametz on פסח. Pesach However, יצא זו שאין שיריה ניכרין. yatza zo
she-ein shiyareiha nikkarin. So now, let's if it became
חמץ from something that's תלוש, I don't really care, he's
saying that forget the fact that once I had שעת הכושר sha'at
hakosher which means now it's okay even though it became חמץ on
פסח. But if right now when I'm separating תרומה and it's חמץ,
okay, so I separated תרומה for the כהן kohen from this stuff
that's חמץ. But is it now, is now the rest of it
permissible to me?
Is it? No, of course not because it's חמץ. I can't have
it on
פסח. So יצא זו שאין שיריה ניכרין. yatza zo she-ein shiyareiha nikkarin.
So therefore, what he's saying
is that it won't work. So even, so as opposed to the
opinion before that we were just talking about that said the only
time it's a problem if it became חמץ בתלוש, I mean במחובר,
right? When it was still attached to the ground, became חמץ. He's
saying based on this פסוק because of ראשית reishit that even if
it became חמץ when it was תלוש, it won't work because it's
not מתיר mattir anyway. And the פסוק is basically telling you that
by separating תרומה you're מתיר mattir the rest of it. In this
case, you're not מתיר mattir the rest of it for anybody because
it's still חמץ. So he disagrees.
So, it's like חמץ isn't considered food.
Right, that's basically his point. ואתא רב אחא בר אויא קמיה דרב
חסדא ויתיב ואמר משמיה דרבי יוחנן.
ve-ata Rav Acha bar Avya kamei de-Rav Chisda ve-yativ ve-amar
mishmeih de-Rabbi Yochanan. So very, very interesting ruling. So anyway, so this
was the ruling and eventually it came in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, just remember
that. ענבים שנטמאו. anavim she-nitma'u. So we know that
one
of the things that you bring to the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash are
נסכים, nesachim, right? נסכים nesachim are stuff that you pour. And נסכים
nesachim can be aside from
ניסוך המים, nisuch hamayim, which is on סוכות, Sukkot, you generally are
מנסך menassech wine, right? You know, that we say that all the
time in our
קרבנות. korbanot. However, check out this ruling, you never would have expected
this. ענבים שנטמאו דרכן פחות פחות מכביצה ויינן כשר לנסכים. anavim she-nitma'u
darchan pachot pachot mi-kebeitzah ve-yeinan kasher le-nesachim.
Amazing. So let's say I have טמא tamei grapes. You would have
thought that's it, I can't bring that into the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash any way, shape or form. No, what you can do
is you press it, obviously that's the only way you get wine,
of course, you press the grapes, as long as you press like
less than... less than an egg's volume at a time, the
wine
that'll eventually come out, the juice which will turn into wine that
comes out of it is actually כשר kasher for נסכים. nesachim. Amazing,
right? I don't like that.
I don't get that.
Yeah, so we're going to explain to it. We're going to explain
it as to how that would work. And רמב"ם Rambam holds that
way? Yeah, this is the פסק, psak, which I'm like, how is
that possible? But basically, so the point is,
because if I've got, if I'm...
yeah, no, we'll go with it. Okay. But say, I mean, your
problem... I'm sure the problem, your problem is exactly what is bothering
the rest of us, so mention it.
Yeah, so if I am טמא אהל, tamei ohel, I'm an... or
טמא מת. tamei meit. Yeah, טמא מת, tamei meit, sorry. I'm an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. I'm not an אב, av, I'm an
אבי אבות. avi... avi... avi avot. You're what?
No, the מת meit is אבי אבות. avi avot. The טמא מת
tamei meit is an אב הטומאה.
av hatumah. So I'm an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Right. I touch
the press, which is a כלי, kli, it becomes a ראשון, rishon,
and the food that touches it is a שני. sheni. Good. And
therefore,
even if it's חולין, chulin, it's a
שני.
sheni. Right. So now, the way this אוקימתא okimta was set up
is, first of all, what are you pressing it with? The wood
is called, it's פשוטי כלי עץ. pshutei klei eitz. פשוטי כלי עץ
pshutei klei eitz are not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So you're using,
basically the point is that you're using like this wood slab, let's
say, that is not going to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So
the wood that you're using to press... so you're not going to
make the wood טמא. tamei. And also...
because it's not really a כלי?
kli? Because, yeah, somehow this wood isn't... that's how they set this
up. Because I was looking into that too. I mean, that's what
I was reading about, that that's the only way they were able
to explain this, that you're using a כלי kli to press that's
not going to be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, and the only way
that would work is if it's עץ. eitz. And also,
because there should be a problem of משקים. mashkim. I'm very careful
not to touch the משקים, mashkim, because right, because I can טמא
tamei the משקים, mashkim, and the משקים mashkim would... that'd be the
end of it, right? So I'm not touching the משקים. mashkim. So
that's how we set this up. But there's still... but wait, but
still,
why aren't the... why isn't the juice in the grapes טמא, tamei,
right? You touch the grapes, the juice is inside. So why isn't
that טמא tamei right away? Right? It's all one and the same.
We're saying the grape is טמא tamei but the juice isn't, right?
The juice is in the grape, it's just a matter of getting
it out. So why doesn't the juice become טמא tamei right away?
So the point is, and we're going to say this explicitly in
a second, is that the juice is considered almost like a separate
entity from the grape.
Right?
View it
as like a cup of water, right? You're not going to say
like the cup is the water, the water is in the cup.
So too, the juice is in the grape. It's not considered like
a grape with juice, so to speak. It's considered juice in a
grape, right? You get the conceptual distinction? Yeah, I get the... I
don't... I mean, whether or not you agree with it, I mean,
but that's the way you have to explain it. And also,
since it's water in a cup,
so you need a minimum... dealing with שיעורים, shiurim, you need a
minimum... in order for, let's say, getting going with my example,
just... this isn't the way it works, but let's... you need a
minimum size of cup, so to speak, to טמא tamei the water.
So you need a minimum size of אוכל ochel to טמא tamei
the משקה. mashkeh. And that is a כביצה. k'beitzah. So that's why
he's saying פחות מכביצה. pachot m'kbeitzah. So if I have less than
a
ביצה's, beitzah an egg's volume worth of these grapes, right? So again,
I
haven't... the כלי kli that I'm pressing isn't מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah,
I'm not touching the juice, the juice is considered in the grape
and not part of it, so to speak, right? And I've less
than... and the אוכל ochel isn't going to מטמא metamei the משקה,
mashkeh, because remember the אוכל ochel was what was טמא, tamei, because
you've less than a volume of egg. So apparently it can't... this
what we're saying now, which maybe is a matter of debate, but
the minimum volume
of אוכל ochel being מטמא, metamei, making something else טמא, tamei, would
be an egg. So therefore, this is why it's okay, right? Obviously
it's a lot of assumptions over here that you have to hold
by, but if you hold by all that, and apparently we do,
because that's the פסק, psak, then you can get something טהור tahor
out of something that's טמא, tamei, even טהור to be, you know,
on the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Maybe that's a nice מוסר mussar
message, right? Something comes from טמא, tamei, it could be even on
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. There's hope for all the rest of
us as טמאים tameim as we may view ourselves. So anyway, אמר
קסבר, ama kasavar, אמר קסבר. ama kasavar. Now I'm going to be
what we discussed outside, now I'm going to be inside, although again,
there's a lot more that was said that's not in here. אמר
קסבר ama kasavar משקין מפקד פקידי. mashkin mifkad pikidi. It's sort of
a... it's like contained by it. It's not absorbed. Again, like I
mentioned, it's juice in the grape, not juice in the grape... I
mean, yeah, juice in the grape. So it doesn't become טמא. tamei.
So okay, so if they're separate, then when can it become טמא?
tamei? So when one can only... possibly טמא tamei the juice like
when you squeeze it out, when the juice is no longer in
the grape. And then והיכי שחת ליה ליתא
לשיעוריה? veheichi shakht leh leta l'shiurei? But but our case, you know,
the juice would never become טמא tamei since the grape since when
when it comes out ליתא לשיעוריה leta l'shiurei there's not enough of
grape left because it's not left, there's not enough grape because I'm
doing it פחות פחות מכביצה. pachot pachot m'kabeitzah. So then אי הכי
ee hachi so they say ah so then if that's the case
אי הכי כביצה נמי ee hachi k'beitzah nami I can even say
that you said that only criteria is that it's less than a
כביצה k'beitzah because in a כביצה beitzah it would be too much
because then it's enough to be מטמא. metamei. But he's saying actually
even a כביצה beitzah which should still be fine as דתנן טמא
מת שסחט זיתים וענבים כביצה מכוונת טהורים. dtanan tamei met sheshakhat zeitim
v'anavim k'beitzah mukhvenet tehorim. So טמא מת
tamei met who who squeezed these grapes or actually actually it's olives
or these grapes even if it's a כביצה beitzah an exact כביצה
beitzah not more but if it's exactly a כביצה beitzah it should
still be
טהור. So okay so why are you saying that it has to
be why are you saying a second ago that it's only if
it's less than a כביצה? k'beitzah? So he's saying הכא דיעבד הכא
לכתחילה hakha d'ye'avad hakha l'chatchilah that's only בדיעבד
but this is לכתחילה l'chatchilah גזירה דילמא אתי למיעבד יותר
מכביצה.
gzeirah dilma ati l'me'avad yoter
mi'kbeitzah. Okay no I mean you know my teaching was my teaching
was ענבים שנטמאו דורכן פחות פחות מכביצה. anavim shenitmeu dorkhan pachot pachot
m'kabeitzah.
Rabbi Yochanan's teaching was that if it's טמא מת tamei met I
mean
לכתחילה l'chatchilah allowed to you know press it and get and get
a get wine for the נסכים nesakhim on that. But this טמא
מת tamei met is only if he did it at most a
כביצה. k'beitzah. Okay fine so לכתחילה l'chatchilah. we allow you less than
a כביצה. k'beitzah. בדיעבד we allow you up until a כביצה. beitzah.
Okay
and why is that? Why would we not allow you to do
up until a כביצה beitzah if בדיעבד it works? Because then you're
going to do more than a כביצה k'beitzah and more than a
כביצה k'beitzah is certainly a problem right? So גזירה gezeirah maybe the
כביצה beitzah is the question right? כביצה beitzah okay you need more
than a כביצה beitzah to מטמא. metamei. Up until a כביצה beitzah
is okay. But we don't want to you know we don't want
you to get so close to a כביצה beitzah because then maybe
you'll do more than a כביצה k'beitzah so less than a כביצה
k'beitzah we'll say it's okay even לכתחילה. l'chatchilah Up to a כביצה
beitzah we'll say it's even okay בדיעבד but more than that is
not okay at all. So okay so anyway that was so that
was Rabbi Yochanan's teaching. We had a challenge to it but then
we got out of it but basically Rabbi Yochanan's teaching is as
it stands that you're allowed to you know לכתחילה be דורך dorekh
it as long as it's less than a כביצה beitzah as long
as it's less than a כביצה. beitzah. So אמר ליה רב חסדא
מן ציית לך ולרבי יוחנן רבך amar lei rav chisda man tza'is
lakh u'l'rabbi yochanan rabakh ah who
is going to listen to you and this ruling of Rabbi Yochanan
your rabbi? Quite dismissive. And we shouldn't follow Rabbi Yochanan and he
disputes Rabbi Yochanan. So וכי תימא שבהם היכן הלכה vechi tima shebahem
heikhan halkha
you what do you mean you're saying that somehow this this juice
remember the whole point of it was the juice considered like separate
from the grape. So he's saying what the טומאה tumah where does
the טומאה tumah of that was in these grapes go? You're saying
it somehow
disappeared meaning when you got out the juice? So obviously by him
saying that אמר קסבר משקין מיבלע בליעי amar kasavar mashkin mibla bleei
if he he's saying that the טומאה tumah never just disappeared that
means he's saying that the that you know it's like all one
and the same like juice is in the grape the grape you
know it's part of the grape so when the grape became טמא
tamei the juice became טמא tamei so just by squeezing it out
isn't going to help you any. ובכל זמן דאיתהו לאוכלא איתהו למשקה
b'chalman d'it'hu l'okhla it'hu l'mashkeh and the most a grape became טמא
tamei the juice became טמא tamei with it as well. So אמר
ליה so he's saying what? So he's saying by you saying that
obviously you're holding that the that it's considered בלוע balua right? You're
saying ואת לא תסברא דמשקין מיפקד פקידי v'at lo tisavra mashkin mifkad
pikdi what you don't hold what we were saying before that the
juice is considered separate than the grapes? והתנן טמא מת שסחט זיתים
וענבים מכוונת כביצה טהורים vehatnan tamei met sheshakhat zeitim v'anavim mukhvenet k'beitzah
tehorim right?
What did we just say a second ago that if a טמא
מת tamei met is דורך dorekh these זיתים zeitim and ענבים anavim
even a כביצה beitzah
is okay. אי אמרת בשלמא מיפקד פקידי im amart bishlama mifkad pikdi
if you say what I say that it's considered separate משום הכי
טהורים mishum hakhi tehorim אלא אי אמרת מיבלע בליעי אמאי טהורים?
ela ee amart mibla bleei
amai tehorim? So why would it work basically what he's saying right?
How do you explain that one? He says הכא במאי עסקינן בענבים
שלא הוכשרו hakha be'mai askinan ba'anavim shelo hukhsharu ah okay because in
other words again like
but that wasn't the case
he's saying that that's how he's explaining it. אמר ליה הכא במאי
עסקינן בענבים שלא הוכשרו amar lei hakha be'mai askinan ba'anavim shelo hukhsharu
the only way that can work again only just because as opposed
to let's say a let's say a someone who is טמא מת
tamei met touches you right? You're not you know he can make
you טמא tamei he can make you you touch a מת met
right? It's not like you're הוכשר mukhshar it's not like you have
to have water on you in order to become טמא. tamei. You
touch the מת met you touch the מת. met. But food needs
to be הוכשר hukhshar and food won't necessarily just become טמא tamei
you know we're always talking about food becoming טמא tamei but yes
you know we it becomes טמא tamei through the שבעה משקין shiva
mashkin right? One of them being let's say water or in this
case the grape would become טמא tamei through the juice but it
needs the medium of of something. So if I just have your
regular grape and the טמא מת tamei met touches it if there
was no water on it let's you know meaning I plucked it
and then
I
So then ואימת מכשרי דכי סחטיה דהוא. ve-eimat mechashrei de-chi sachatei de-hu.
So okay fine, then when how could it possibly then be הוכשר
huchshar for טומאה? tumah? With the juice of the grape when it
comes out? ואימת מכשרי דכי סחטיה דהוא? ve-eimat mechashrei de-chi sachatei de-hu?
בציר ליה שיעורא. batsir lei shiura. But but if it's ביצה מכוונת,
beitzah mechouvenet, right? By the time I actually press it, I've now
compressed it to a volume less than an egg. And we mentioned
that you need a minimum size of
a ביצה beitzah
in order to conduct this טומאה, tumah, right? So that was our
case. So our case is that's how we managed to get out
of it. So I can say even that it's that it's considered
בלוע. balua. So wait, so then so then why is that? So
the grapes didn't become טמא tamei is basically what we're saying because
they were never הוכשר. huchshar. And then you're going to say, okay,
so now everything will become טמא tamei once it's הוכשר huchshar through
the juice that comes out, because again, this is a טמא מת
tamei met that's touching these grapes.
But
the point is the only way the juice will come out is
if you're compressing the grapes. And this is a case where we
started out with exactly a ביצה's beitzah worth of grapes. And when
you compress it, it's now less than a ביצה's beitzah volume. אי
לא
תימא הכי, ei
lo teima
hachi, and if you don't say that, הי דתניא, hai de-tanya,
this is recalling what we mentioned yesterday, תרומת תותין זיתים וענבים שנטמאו,
שאין בהן לא היתר אכילה ולא היתר הסקה. terumat tutin zeytin va-anavim
she-nitme'u she-ein bahen lo heter achila va-lo heter hasaka. Remember we
were talking about before the other day about is it based on
the volume of an
olive-based or is it based on the value of a פרוטה? perutah?
And then we tried to go back and forth about תרומה and
חמץ to say a value, does it not have a value? And
we ended up comparing it to, you know we said that it's
for you and not for like fuel, right? So we compared it
to the חמץ תרומה on פסח to תרומת תותין זיתים וענבים שנטמאו,
terumat tutin zeytin va-anavim she-nitme'u, they became טמא. tamei. Because you're not
going to use it
for הסקה hasaka because, you know, it's too moist, it's not going
to be good firewood, and you can't eat it because it's טמא.
tamei. So we compared it to תרומת תותין זיתים וענבים שנטמאו terumat
tutin zeytin va-anavim she-nitme'u, שאין בהן לא היתר אכילה ולא היתר הסקה.
she-ein bahen lo heter achila va-lo heter hasaka.
But he's saying what do you
mean, אין לו היתר אכילה? ein lo heter achila? היתר אכילה נמי
אית בה? heter achila nami it ba? דבאי דדרכי להו פחות פחות
מכביצה? de-ba'i de-darech lehu pachat pachat mi-kebeitzah? So what do you mean
you can't eat תרומה טמאה? If you're trying to say, you know
there's a way to eat it, fine, I can't pop the olive
into my mouth because we're talking about טמאים teme'im olives, but if
you just if you were just saying that you can get out
of it
by squeezing it, right? So why don't you squeeze it here too?
So you know I can use the olive oil, I can use
the grape juice or the wine.
But but we don't say that. So therefore he's saying I hold
that it's considered all part of it, right? That was the, if
you consider it all part of it, you can't say the juice
is separate than the grape, or the juice is separate than the
olive. It's all one and it's all one together. So that's why.
So therefore I don't buy what you said in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it's possible to squeeze this
fluid juice
out and and for it to be okay.
And in any case,
that's not the original case.
ענבים שנטמאו. anavim she-nitme'u.
I know, I know. It doesn't sound like it,
but incredibly, according to some, the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens according to
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So
okay, so fine. So I mean not fine, but you know what
we're up to right now is what if the gist of this
is do we buy what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying, right?
That that you're allowed to extract the juice and that'll be okay
even to to go on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? And only way again,
only way to say that you consider it, you know, the you're
only doing it פחות מכביצה, pachat mi-kebeitzah, you don't so the way
to do it again the עץ eitz that you suppress it is
not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, you're doing less than a volume of
stuff that would מטמא metamei something else and the juice is considered
separate from the grape. That's that's all the assumptions over and we're
doing it again because it's like you know there are many layers
of assumptions and the alternative is saying that no when the grape
becomes טמא tamei the juice becomes טמא, tamei, it's all one and
the same, right? And so he just cited a pretty, you know,
good reason as to why we would say it's all considered one
and the same because we said that this, you know, this berry
stuff once it becomes טמא, tamei, that's the end of it, right?
But he's saying no, well, you know, if according to you there
should be a way out, just squeeze it, right? As long as
you do less than, you know, than an egg's volume, you should
be okay. But we don't say that, which means then I don't
buy anything what you were just saying. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so
he's saying no, actually, it's the reason why why you can't use
this, you know, this this berry, these these טמאים teme'im berries
is is not because it's considered טמא tamei right away, but דדילמא
אתי בה
דתקלה,
de-dilma ati ba
de-takala, because what we're we're going to say, okay, okay, maybe really
you can squeeze. Always the juices.
But if you squeeze the juices and you're going to say, alright,
well, obviously I can use these berries, let me go eat it.
That you can't do, right? The only way the only way you're
allowed to get any benefit out of it is by getting the
juice out. But you're not going to know juice you're going to
say what's the difference between the juice and eating the fruit. You'll
eat the fruit and everyone agrees cannot be eaten because it's the
fruit is טמא. tamei. Right? Again the whole point was maybe you
can get the משקה mashke to be טהור through the way רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. So he's saying no that's not a proof.
You're trying to say that the fact that you can't eat it
is because it's really טמא tamei and it all becomes טמא tamei
together. I'm going to say really you should be able to squeeze
out the juice so why don't we and so why are we
considering it a total loss? We're just worried about what that's going
to lead to but מדינא mi'dina you that you should be able
to do that. So מדינא. mi'dina. אמרי ליה אביי ומי חיישינן לתקלה.
amrei lei Abaye umi
khaishinan letakala. So so אביי Abaye says wait wait are you sure
that we're actually worried about this
תקלה? takala? והתניא מדליקין בפת ובשמן של תרומה שנטמאת.
ve'ha tanya madlikin bipat
uveshemen shel teruma shenitmeit. We're allowed to use שמן shemen that of
תרומה that's נטמאת nitmeit right? So if you're so worried about the
תקלה takala you're going to say oh well the oil's טמא tamei
the oil came from an olive if I can use the oil
why can't I use the olive?
Right? And in which case it should be forbidden but no we
say we say you know if we're really worried about תקלה takala
then why are we allowing you to burn תרומה oil? Right? You're
allowed to use it as fuel.
So
אמרי ליה פת זריק ליה ביני עצים. amrei lei pat zarik lei
beina eitzim. So the way we're allowing you to do that is
is we actually are concerned about תקלה takala and the reason why
we're allowing you to
use this שמן shemen as fuel or the bread as fuel is
because you're going to make it disgusting. You're not going to come
to eat it is what we're saying. פת זריק ליה ביני עצים
שמן של תרומה רמי ליה בכלי מאוס. pat zarik lei beina eitzim
shemen shel teruma ramei lei bikhli ma'us. You're going to basically you're
going to do you're going to you
know forget about the eating the olive I mean if you actually
you know I mean if you actually drink the olive oil or
use it in your salads eating it too. So so we're not
so we're allowing you to use it as fuel because we're going
to make the אוקימתא yukimta in a way that that you're not
going to come to consume it because you're putting this oil in
something disgusting so you're not going to put it on your salad
it's in this you know dirty bowl. And פת pat and the
פת pat you're using as firewood you're not going to come to
eat it because you're throwing it you know basically in the you
know wood heap it's you know getting it all all disgusting and
dirty. Basically you're doing something to it that you're not going to
come to eat it.
But isn't what what's the the original חשש chashash with the with
the strawberries is what? That if you have the ability to maybe
do it little by little and then be able to to use
it
you'll come to eat the strawberry.
You'll come to eat the strawberry. Because why?
Because you're going to say what's the difference between I presumably I
mean it doesn't say why but but
before you do the little by
little no or maybe or even like you know you're saying like
oh okay I'm using this juice it's now טהור so if the
juice is okay why isn't the fruit okay? And the fruit isn't
okay so you'll come to eat the fruit.
That was our that was our concern.
But yet but the question is but yet we allow you to
I know I mean it's really doesn't you know it's not completely
convincing to me but we're saying but yet we still allow you
to to use this oil and burn it. So the answer is
okay well the way we're allowing you to burn the oil is
is because you put it in something that you're not going to
come to eat it in. You're just not going to use it.
Okay but you know but still you know maybe why aren't we
worried that if you allow you to use the oil you know
we're allowing you know why aren't we worried about the olive that
it came from? Maybe you don't have the olive it came from
anymore I don't know.
Yeah I mean look to me it sounds sounds very crazy but
that's what we're saying.
שמן של תרומה רמי ליה בכלי מאוס shemen shel teruma ramei lei
bikhli ma'us so fine you threw your your bread into the firewood
so you're not going to come to eat it. You put your
your olive oil in something you know pretty disgusting you're not going
to come to eat it either. שמן של תרומה רמי ליה בכלי
מאוס.
shemen shel teruma ramei lei
bikhli ma'us. So therefore the point actually is that normally we would
be חושש לתקלה choshesh letakala by saying oh you know how do
you get out of
the olive oil case aren't you חושש לתקלה choshesh letakala there? And
the answer is yes we actually are חושש לתקלה choshesh letakala and
the only way we're allowing you to do it is because you're
putting it in something that won't lead that you know that's basically
preventing you from that because you're putting it in something you're not
going to use but normally we would be חושש לתקלה. choshesh letakala.
So alright so the question is you want to stop now or
do you want to go on a little bit? I'm just going
to stay in the שיעור shiur
downstairs.
Okay it's a good place to stop anyway because to stop anyway
because we're going to we're going to review this a little bit
more. גופא gufa we're going to review this a little bit more.
Anyway so the point the point being that you know again like
this whole
other עמוד amud over here was was getting into whether or not
the juice the juice is okay the first opinion said it's okay
because you know again all these steps I'm not going to review
the other opinion is it's not okay we we had a number
of challenges back and forth and then eventually you know we managed
to get out of it. Although although it sounded it really didn't
sound so much like a רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but he managed
to wheedle himself in and out of it all like the other
cases
are the other cases it's not
הוכשר huchshar or getting out or or we managed to prevent a
תקלה takala aspect. So that's that's what we ended up saying. יישר
כוח.
Yashar koach. מזל טוב. Mazel tov. Thank you.